Association of Research Libraries Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Association of Research Libraries Records 1932-1979
MSS54718
Association of Research Libraries
11,000 items 44 containers 17.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Organization of research libraries in the United States and Canada. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, reports, financial records, printed matter, and miscellaneous items relating to the association's membership and its assessment and evaluation projects and services on behalf of client institutions.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
Organizations
Association of Research Libraries.; Farmington Plan.; Library of Congress.; National Agricultural Library (U.S.); National Library of Medicine (U.S.)
Subjects
Academic libraries.; Acquisition of foreign publications--United States.; Agricultural libraries.; Cooperative acquisition of library materials.; Education, Higher.; Libraries--Canada.; Libraries--Societies, etc.; Libraries--United States.; Library catalogs.; Medical libraries.; National libraries.; Newspapers on microfilm.; Public libraries.; Research libraries.; Research.; Special libraries.
Titles
Public Law 480 program.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The records of the Association of Research Libraries were given to the Library of Congress by the association between 1974 and 1982.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the Association of Research Libraries are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Organizational History
The Association of Research Libraries was formed in 1932 for the purpose of improving the collections and services of its member libraries in support of higher education and research. Its membership consists of larger university libraries; research libraries in the United States and Canada, including the three national libraries of the United States: the Library of Congress, the National Agricultural Library, and the National Library of Medicine; and public and special libraries with large research collections.
The association undertakes a variety of activities, including serving as a representative for its members in matters relating to the federal government, international agencies, and other library associations, as well as engaging in cooperative projects and studies with other academic and research organizations. Among the more important projects sponsored or supported by the association are the Farmington Plan, the Public Law 480 program, the National Program for Acquisitions and Cataloging, the Foreign Newspaper Microfilm Project, the annual publication of Dissertation Abstracts, and the establishment of the Center for Chinese Research Materials and the Slavic Bibliographic and Documentation Center.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Association of Research Libraries span the years 1932-1979 and document the efforts of the association to improve the collections and services of member research libraries in North America. The collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, reports, financial records, printed matter, and miscellaneous items concerning the organizational structure and administration of the association. The records reflect on membership requirements and admittances, the deliberations of internal and cooperative committees, relationships with affiliated organizations, and various projects administered by the association, including the Farmington Plan, the Public law 480 program, the Foreign Newspaper Microfilm Project, and the publication of the first Library of Congress catalog initiated and sponsored by the association.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by subject in the order as the items were originally described and housed.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm82054718
Container List
- General (Box 1)
  - 1932-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 2)
- General correspondence (Box 2)
  - 1947-1949 (Box 2)
  - 1949-1951 (Box 3)
  - 1951-1953 (Box 4)
  - 1954-1959 (Box 5)
  - 1959-1962 (Box 6)
- Fiscal records, 1933-1962 (Box 7)
  - Vouchers and receipts, 1933-1937 (Box 7)
  - Dues and membership list, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Account 8069 (Box 7)
  - Membership dues (Box 7)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 7)
    - 1956 (Box 8)
  - Microcard orders of minutes (Box 8)
  - Sales (Box 8)
    - Farmington Plan (Box 8)
      - Final report (Box 8)
      - Handbook (Box 8)
    - Minutes of meetings (Box 8)
  - Deposits (Box 8)
  - Financial statements (Box 8)
  - Orders sent (Box 8)
  - Clearinghouse forms, sale of (Box 8)
- Organization membership (Box 9)
  - Membership and representation (Box 9)
  - Digest, minutes of meetings (Box 9)
  - Weber, index to minutes (Box 9)
  - Use and distribution of minutes (Box 9)
  - Reorganization, 1946 ballot (Box 9)
  - Admission of John Crerar Library, Chicago, Ill. (Box 10)
  - Admission of Army Medical and Agriculture (Box 10)
  - Reconstitution of membership, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Old member (Box 10)
  - Reconstitution of membership, new nominees (Box 10)
  - Dartmouth, N.H., 1952 (Box 11)
  - Membership, 1953-1957 (Box 11)
  - Potential members, 1961-1962 (Box 11)
  - Membership, 1962 (Box 11)
  - Reorganization (Box 11)
  - Invitations, representatives, and inaugurations (Box 12)
  - Association list and general (Box 12)
  - Dix phone calls (Box 12)
  - Executive secretive (Box 12)
    - Candidates (Box 12)
    - General (Box 12)
  - Eugene Power, advisory committee concerning microfilming operation in Moscow, USSR (Box 12)
  - Press releases (Box 12)
  - Tax exemption application (Box 12)
  - Constitution, working papers (Box 12)
  - Incorporation, correspondence (Box 12)
  - Committee memberships (Box 12)
  - Members (Box 12)
  - Constitutions (Box 12)
  - Reorganization, 1961-1962 (Box 12)
  - Meetings (Box 13)
    - Chicago, Ill., 1932-1933, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Montreal, Canada, 1934, June (Box 13)
    - Washington, D.C., 1934, Dec. (Box 13)
    - Denver, Colo., 1935, July (Box 13)
    - Chicago, Ill., 1935, Dec. (Box 13)
    - Richmond, Va., 1936, May (Box 13)
    - Chicago, Ill., 1936, Dec. (Box 13)
    - New York, N.Y., 1937, July (Box 13)
    - Chicago, Ill., 1937, Dec. (Box 13)
    - Kansas, 1938, July (Box 13)
    - Unknown, twelfth meeting (Box 13)
    - San Francisco, Calif., 1939, July (Box 13)
    - Chicago, Ill., Dec. 1939 (Box 13)
  - Extra copies (Box 13)
    - Circular letters (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - General (Box 14)
  - Farmington Plan Advisory Committee, minutes of meeting, 1961 (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous projects (Box 15)
  - Wilson Co., service basis, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Charge study (Box 15)
  - Price and Raney reports (Box 15)
  - Doctoral dissertation (Box 15)
  - List, 1939 (Box 15)
  - Microfilming of master's thesis (Box 15)
  - Master's thesis list (Box 16)
  - Committee on Indexing and Abstracting (Box 16)
  - Doctoral dissertations, 1947-1953 (Box 16)
  - Committee on the Publication and Distribution of Thesis, 1951 (Box 16)
  - Dissertation lists (Box 16)
    - Association of Research Libraries (Box 16)
    - Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. (Box 16)
  - Advisory Committee on the Publication and Recording of Dissertations (Box 17)
  - Modern Language Association project, Robbins (Box 17)
  - Pastor index (Box 17)
  - Paul, James C. N., Institute of Legal Research (Box 17)
  - Author index for Poole (Box 17)
  - Preservation of confidential material (Box 17)
  - Price (Box 17)
  - Rusk, George Y. (Box 17)
  - Silver, Henry (Box 17)
  - Harry Truman Library, Independence, Mo. (Box 17)
  - National code hearings, publication (Box 17)
  - Clearinghouse for interlibrary loans (Box 17)
  - Inter-American Library meetings (Box 18)
  - Interlibrary loan code (Box 18)
  - International Conference on Cataloging Principles (Box 18)
  - Kraus, Abtailung A. (Box 18)
  - Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. (Box 18)
    - Cooperative purchase of European books (Box 18)
    - Librarianship (Box 18)
    - Printing of catalog (Box 18)
  - Librarians Liaison Committee (Box 18)
  - Code authorities, National Recovery Administration (Box 18)
  - Durable paper (Box 19)
  - Edwards music republishing (Box 19)
  - Encyclopedia of SS (Box 19)
  - Florence agreement (Box 19)
  - Evans project (Box 19)
  - Folklore (Box 19)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H. (Box 19)
  - Alien property custodian (Box 20)
  - American imprints inventory (Box 20)
  - Autonomy of law libraries (Box 20)
  - Biological abstracts projects, service basis charge (Box 20)
  - Chemical abstracts (Box 20)
  - Chinese imports, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Cost of books index (Box 20)
  - Commerce Department export regulations (Box 20)
  - Miscellany (Box 20)
- Committees and projects (Box 21)
  - Board on Acquisition of Library Material (Box 21)
  - Bibliographical control of microforms (Box 21)
  - Committee on Bibliography (Box 21)
  - Customs, 1946-1954 (Box 22)
  - Documentation and Information Retrieval Committee (Box 23)
  - Committee to Examine Legal Aspects of Securing Foreign Documents (Box 23)
  - Interm Committee on Export of Library Material (Box 23)
  - Committee on Foreign Newspapers, microfilming project (Box 23)
  - Foreign Official Gazette Committee (Box 23)
  - Committee on the High Cost of German Books and Periodicals (Box 23)
  - Committee on Library Privileges and Fees (Box 23)
  - Manuscript accessions (Box 23)
    - General (Box 23)
    - List (Box 23)
  - Committee on Cooperative Microfilm Projects (Box 24)
  - Committee on Microfilm (Box 24)
  - Cooperation (Box 24)
  - Microphotography (Box 24)
  - Microfilming of newspapers (Box 24)
  - Newspapers on microfilm (Box 24)
  - Committee on Microfilm Lending (Box 24)
  - Committee on Microtext Standards (Box 24)
  - Committee on Midwest Group's Proposal (Box 25)
  - Index to monograph series (Box 25)
  - National conference (Box 25)
  - Committee on National Needs in Time of Crisis (Box 25)
  - National Union Catalog (Box 25)
    - Manuscript collections (Box 25)
    - Mechanization (Box 25)
  - Committee to Prevent Post War Competition in Books Purchases (Box 26)
  - Committee on Protection of Cultural and Scientific Resources (Box 26)
  - Public law 480 (Box 26)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 26)
    - Letters of support to congressmen (Box 26)
  - Committee on Reichman Proposal (Box 26)
  - Committee on Reproduction (Box 26)
  - Reprints, Kaplin (Box 26)
  - Committee on Research Libraries and the Library of Congress (Box 27)
  - Russian Translation Committee (Box 27)
  - Committee on Serials in Research Fields, 1952, (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - National Committee on Renaissance Studies (Box 28)
  - Statistics (Box 28)
  - Committee on Statistics (Box 28)
  - Transliteration (Box 28)
  - Committee on Unesco Affairs (Box 28)
  - Union list of serials (Box 28)
  - Joint Committee on Union List of Serials (Box 28)
  - Committee on the Use of Manuscripts by Visiting Scholars (Box 28)
- Associations, affiliations, and joint committees (Box 29)
  - Affiliated organizations (Box 29)
  - American Library Association (Box 29)
    - Committee on Implementation of National Plans (Box 29)
    - Committee on Standardization of Library Supplies and Equipment, Z85 (Box 29)
    - Committee Z39 (Box 29)
    - Councillor (Box 29)
    - General (Box 29)
    - Library Education Division newsletter (Box 29)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 29)
    - General (Box 29)
    - Project on microfilm (Box 30)
  - American Documentation Institute and Science, Watson Davis (Box 30)
  - Association of College and Research Libraries (Box 30)
  - Conference on American Library (Box 30)
  - Resources on southern Asia (Box 30)
  - Conference on Science Manuscripts (Box 30)
  - Council of Graduate Schools in the United States (Box 30)
  - Council on Library Resources (Box 30)
    - Grant (Box 30)
    - Grant request (Box 31)
  - Council of National Library Associations (Box 31)
    - General, 1952-1962, (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - Joint committees (Box 31)
      - United States libraries and the federal government (Box 31)
      - Safeguarding library material (Box 32)
      - Projects to foundations (Box 32)
      - Visiting foreign libraries (Box 32)
      - Fair use in copying (Box 32)
  - Joint committees (Box 32)
    - Governments (Box 32)
    - Documentation service (Box 32)
    - Increased cost of Library of Congress cards (Box 32)
    - Importation Advisory Committee (Box 32)
    - Indexing and abstracting (Box 32)
    - Library education, minutes of meeting, 1961 (Box 32)
    - Library work as a career (Box 32)
    - Microcards (Box 33)
    - Polibiblon (Box 33)
    - Princeton University, Princeton, N.J. (Box 33)
    - Reproduction of bibliographic and reference works (Box 33)
    - Reproduction of enemy publications (Box 33)
  - Overhead costs (Box 33)
    - Article by Logsdon (Box 33)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 33)
    - Library overhead cost, 1964 (Box 34)
      - Current material (Box 34)
      - Institutional reports, file no. 2 (Box 34)
  - National Science Foundation (Box 34)
    - Grant requests (Box 34)
      - Columbia School of Library Science, New York, N.Y. (Box 34)
      - Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio (Box 34)
    - Grant (Box 34)
    - Materials, 1961 (Box 34)
    - Liaison Committee (Box 34)
      - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 34)
      - Meetings, 1961-1962, (2 folders) (Box 34)
      - Reports (Box 35)
    - Advisory Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 35)
  - National Postal Committee for Educational and Cultural Materials, postal rates (Box 35)
  - Standard Conference of National and University Libraries (Box 35)
  - United States Book Exchange (Box 35)
  - Board of Directors (Box 36)
  - Advisory Committee, 1934-1961 (Box 36)
- Meetings (Box 37)
  - 1934-1943 (Box 37)
  - 1944-1954 (Box 38)
  - 1955-1961 (Box 39)
- Legislation (Box 40)
  - Legislative matters (Box 40)
  - Foreign Agents Registration Act (Box 40)
  - Congressional hearings (Box 40)
  - H.R. 6, Walter's bill (Box 40)
  - H.R. 7927 (Box 40)
  - H.R. 8900, conference report, academic bill (Box 40)
  - H.R. 11823 (Box 40)
  - S. 1726 (Box 40)
- Farmington Plan (Box 41)
  - Advisory Committee meeting, 1961 (Box 41)
  - General (Box 41)
  - Handbook (Box 41)
  - Newsletter (Box 41)
  - Chronological file (Box 41)
    - 1959, Sept. (Box 41)
    - 1949-1959 (Box 42)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 43)
  - Farmington proposal (Box 43)
  - Princeton meeting, 1959 (Box 43)
  - Council on Library Resources grant, 1959 (Box 43)
  - Joint Committee on African Resources (Box 44)
  - Sub-Committees (Box 44)
    - Africa (Box 44)
    - Far Eastern resources (Box 44)
    - Latin American resources (Box 44)
    - Near and Middle Eastern resources (Box 44)
    - Slavic and East European library material, 1959 (Box 44)
    - Slavic studies, 1958 (Box 44)
    - South Asia (Box 44)
    - Western European library materials (Box 44)